



Professional summary

Samrawit is a public health professional with 12 years of experience in Mentoring, project management, leadership, grant and partnership management, Data use, and advocacy for policy change in areas of HIV/AIDS, SRH/FP and Quality Assurance. She has strong interpersonal communication, team building, and analytical skill.

Samrawit has extensive experience in leading new initiatives, developing strategic documents and guidelines for health system strengthening, Community-level, and Key Population health services.

Currently, Samrawit is working as a field epidemiologist consultant to WHO-Timor Leste, country office. She supports immunization, surveillance of vaccine-preventable diseases, and outbreak investigations and responses in Timor Leste, Southeast Asia.

New challenges, innovation, and data analytic inspire Samrawit. She is a fast learner and passionate to contribute to Universal Health Coverage.

EDUCATION

BSc in public health officer, Hawassa University, Hawassa, Ethiopia, 01-11-2005 to 20-03-2009. Master's in general public health, Adama Science and Technology University, Adama, Ethiopia, 13-11-2013 to 02-07-2015.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

STOP consultant World Health Organization Dili, Timor Leste

July, 2019 – Present Supervisor: Dr PEIRIS, Thelge Sudath Rohana

- Provides technical support to Ministry of Health to improve immunization coverage and Vaccine Preventable Diseases (VPD) surveillance performance.
- Builds capacity of ministry of health, district health office and facility health professionals by mentoring, training, on job orientation and supervision on surveillance and EPI.
- Supports MoH, NiTAG and national EPI working group to revise, formulate and develop national immunization related policies, strategic document, guideline and other working documents aligning with the global and local context.
- Reviews EPI and surveillance data, evaluate performance indicators, give feedback to health facilities and support for improvement.
- Ensures EPI and VPD surveillance related data is collected, analyzed, interpreted and used at each level and feed into the HIMS/DHIS2 timely.
- Supports the district Rapid Response Team in the time of disease outbreak and disasters.
- Develops of COVID-19 surveillance guideline, data capturing and contact tracing tools.
- Oversees effective deployment of COVID-19 vaccine by developing national deployment plan, technical implantation guideline, documentation tools provide training and oversee implementation at different district.

Associate Technical Director, Population Services International (PSI), Ethiopia

May, 2019 – Jul. 2019 **Supervisor: Dr Endale Workalemahu**

 Maintained and fosters strong external relations with strategic partners, such as the Ministry of Health (MOH), FMHACA, EPHI, ICAP, USAID, and local implementing partners.

- Ensured alignment of Local Implementing Partners (LIP) annual work plan and implementation with donor requirements and project KPIs.
- Reviewed and supported project budget management including budget spending trend,
 prepare bi-weekly operating advance request and ensure compliance to donor requirements and proper documentation.
- Supported the team in preparation of Expenditure analysis reports.
- Represented PSI in different national working group like PrEP, Quality Assurance, HIV/AIDS TAG and Recency testing.
- Evidence generated on implementation of Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis and result disseminated to advocate for scale up in the presence of MoH, donors like CDC & USAID, and partners.
- Advocated to scale up PrEP for different target groups and geographical areas.
- Oversaw implementation of innovative approaches to ensure case finding including HIV self-test, Index case testing, social network testing and others.
- Participated in resource mobilization by proposal writing.

Quality Assurance Manager, Population Services International (PSI), Ethiopia,

Mar, 2018 – May. 2019 Addis Ababa, Ethiopia Supervisor: Dr Endale Workalemahu

- Contributed to development of nation HIV/AIDS Prevention, Care and Treament guideline and training manual representing PSI MULU KPP project.
- Participated in selection of 15 Local Implementing parnters (LIPs) to granted for MULU KPP project.
- Contributed to development of annual and 5 years costed work plan to implement integrated SRH services.
- Led role out of PrEP in USAID funded community hubs and government facilities by preparing concept note, implementation manual, job aids and tracking the result to advocate scale up.
- Established Quality Assurance team for PSI and capacitated with on-the-job coaching.
- Ensured implementation of quality integrated SRH service MULU KP implementation towns and Ado 360 project.
- Represented PSI in the East Africa Quality Assurance team and closely work with PSI headquarter FP and QA teams.

- Supervised and mentored regional office teams and Local implementing partners on HIV/AIDS and Family planning quality services.
- Developed and revised Quality Assurance framework for USAID funded Key and Priority Population HIV/AIDS and Adolescent 360 family planning projects.
- Led technology related innovation like Health Network Quality Improvement System (HNQIS) for FP, HIV and NCD projects, and Aspect® software (Timely Viral load reporting and decision-making software).
- Ensured donor rules and regulation are followed by MULU KPP and Ado360 projects.
- Collected reports Bi-Weekly and monthly, clean, verify, analyze and report for leadership team, donor and MoH.

Treatment Linkage and Quality Assurance Manager, Population Services International (PSI), Ethiopia, Addis Ababa, June /2016 – March 2018 Supervisor: Mr Israel Lemma

- Led establishment of 25 Friendly community ART Drop-in-Centers under USAID funded MULU/MARPs project.
- Oversaw procurement and distribution of required; medical supplies and commodities including; drugs, laboratory reagents and supplies, to LIPs and drop-in-centers.
- Ensured the quality of HIV Prevention, Care and Treatment services at PSI-DICs by building the capacity of regional PSI experts and service providers through regular mentoring, training, supervision, SIMS visit, External/Internal quality audit and performance evaluation meetings.
- Developed implementation manual, guideline and SOPs for Community ART.
- Oversaw implementation of innovative approach for case finding, treatment linkage and retention.
- Led partnership of PSI FHI360 (OVC) project and faith based organizations.
- Ensured Local Implementing Partners and PSI offices are exceeding donor requirement and pass SIMS evaluation.
- Developed quality assurance framework and improvement projects, and closely follow implementation success by building the capacity of regional PSI experts and service providers through continues mentoring, supportive supervision, performance review and External/Internal quality audit.
- Led establishment of data entry and analysis platform on DHIS2, and support evidence-based decision-making using M&E reports for quality improvement.

• Participated in the development of proposal for 65M, 5 years MULU follow on BID.

Zonal project coordinator, Columbia University Mailman School of Public Health (ICAP), Ethiopia

Dec /2014 - June /2016,

ping an annual plan, implementation and

Supervisor: Dr Kestebirhan Delele.

- Zonal Health offices supported in developing an annual plan, implementation and performance evaluation.
- Support mentoring hospital to ensure quality and regular mentoring activity for catchment facilities.
- hospitals and big health centers Mentored on HIV, MNCH, TB, and Family planning and Nutrition activities.
- Monthly reporting supported for timeliness, consistency, and correctness through mentoring and data verification.
- Zonal health offices and ART providing health facilities supported to meet the standard using the CDC SIMS checklist.

Zonal Mentor Coordinator, CU-ICAP, Ethiopia, Addis Ababa

March /2013 – Sept /2014,

Supervisor: Dr Tsigereda Kifle

- Led and supervised the West Haragie ICAP PMTCT and M&E team to execute their monthly mentoring, supervision and performance evaluation activities.
- Monthly mentoring team activity plan developed and coordinated.
- Quality of HIV care and treatment service ensured through mentoring and training.
- Timely quality data reporting ensured and data verification conducted.
- Zonal health office expert's capacity builds through on job coaching and training
- Monthly catchment area and performance evaluation meeting facilitated.

Youth center head, Family guidance association of Ethiopia

Dec/ 2012 to March/2013

Supervisor: Mr Birhanu Mohammed

- Planned, coordinated and monitored of youth center activities to provide integrated SRH services focusing on family planning, ANC, HIV and STI services.
- Supervised and mentored 7 of the clinic exprets and Wolkite Town Youth Association members

Public Health Officer at Fitche Hospital, Ethiopia

Oct/2009 - Nov/2012

Supervisor: Dr Sisay Temesgen

• Worked at Fitche Hospital as a clinician to different units like OPDs, MNCH, Family planning, Wards and ART clinic.

- Represented Fitche Hospital in different regional and national meetings as ART clinic focal person.
- Supervised 10 team members of ART clinic and mentored 15 North Shoa Health Centers on HIV Prevention, Care and Treatment services.

Accomplishment

- Led Key population friendly Community ART services in USAID community hubs (Drop-In-Centers) for Female Sex Workers which improves linkage, early treatment initiation and retention of HIV positive FSWs to more than 95%.
- Presented an article on Community ART experience and achievement at AIDS 2018 conference in Amsterdam, Netherlands representing MULU KP project.
- Led initiation of PrEP at selected community hubs and government facilities to Female Sex Workers and discordant couples.
- A 2-million-dollar grant obtained from USAID to integrate family planning service in 25 Drop-In-Centers to Female Sex Workers.

TRAINING AND PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Trainings	Days of training	Organization
Quality assurance in FP/RH	4 days	PSI/Tanzania
National Forum on Quality Improvement	3 days	IHI, in Orlando, Florida
AIDS 2018 conference	5 days	Amsterdam, Netherlands
Comprehensive HIV prevention care and treatment	14 days	ICAP-ETHIOPIA
Clinical mentorship	5 days	ICAP-ETHIOPIA
Quality assurance	3 days	ICAP
Project cycle management	5 days	PSI/Ethiopia
Comprehensive Family planning	13 days	Marie stop's
Behavioral Change Communication	3 days	PSI/Ethiopia
Health Network Quality Improvement System (HNQIS) TOT	3 days	PSI/Ethiopia
DHIS2 end users	5 days	WHO Timor Leste
STOP Transmission of Polio field epidemiology	13 days	CDC and WHO Uganda
TOT for DQA and DQIP in SEARO Countries	4 days	WHO SEARO

Skills – Team building, mentoring, implementing user center designs (UCD), Microsoft office applications, familiar with MS Teams, Zoom, Excel analytics, Pivot table, and IBM Cognos.

References

- Dr PEIRIS, Thelge Sudath Rohana, Technical Officer for Immunization, peirist@who.int +670-78266726
- **Dr Endale Workalemahu, Country Representative,** PSI/Eswatini (Swaziland), endaleti@gmail.com, +251-91-100-2121
- Dr Kesetebirhan Delele (MD,MPH), HIV/Health technical director at FHI360: kesetebirhan@gmail.com, +251-910212658